# YOUNGWON KIM

**Address**: 3801 Brooklyn Ave NE, Seattle, WA 98105 **Phone**: (512) 888-8073 Email: kimyw@uw.edu Website: https://kimyoungwon.github.io/personal\_page

#### **EDUCATION**

Jun 2023 (Expected)	Ph.D., Measurement & Statistics College of Education, University of Washington, Seattle, WA
May 2017	M.A., Educational Psychology  Specialization: Human Development, Culture, & Learning Sciences, University of Texas at Austin, Austin, TX
Feb 2011	B.A., International & Area Studies, Counseling Psychology, & Social Welfare Handong Global University, Pohang-si, Gyeongbuk, South Korea

#### **OVERVIEW**

My methodological interest is focused on the intersections between latent variable models and machine learning algorithms, and my substantive interests center on how these methodologies can promote datadriven educational policy and practice. I am skilled in a variety of statistical modeling approaches for small- and large-scale data, including item response theory, multilevel, structural equation, social network, and time series modeling. Further, I am experienced in data visualization, machine learning methods, and analytic programming using mostly R, Python, and Tableau. Other software includes SPSS, HLM, Stata, SAS, and SQL.

#### **AWARDS/HONORS**

2019	Young Researcher Award, Korean-American Educational Research
	Association (KAERA)

2015 - 2021OTEFE Foundation Scholarship, OTEFE Foundation, Inc.

#### RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Jun 2019 – Present Consultant

### Center for Social Science Computation and Research, University of Statistical Computing Washington, Seattle, WA

- Statistical and programming consulting services to students and faculty from across UW Seattle campus
- Guidance on research designs, data cleaning, data analysis, and use of data analysis and visualization software (Mplus, Python, R, SPSS, and Tableau)
- Remote synchronous and asynchronous workshops on R and SPSS

Research Assistant

May 2018 – Dec 2021 Project on Asian International Graduate Students' Professional Development and Psychological Well-Being, Texas A&M University, College Station, TX (Dr. Koo)

- Interviewed international graduate students and transcribe the interviews
- Coded and analyzed transcripts on the usage of social media, language proficiency, academic achievement, career development, social support, mental and physical health issues of international students
- Contributed to writing proposals for conference presentations and manuscripts for publication

Research Assistant

Mar 2020 – Dec 2020 Teacher Workforce Project, University of Washington, Seattle, WA (Drs. Elfers and Plecki)

- Co-designed and implemented statistical models to examine the teacher workforce in Washington State with respect to teacher retention and mobility
- Co-authored results for presentation, white paper, and publication

### **RESEARCH EXPERIENCE (Cont'd)**

*Jul* 2018 – Sep 2018 Data Wrangler

### Health Sciences Library, University of Washington, Seattle, WA (Dr. Dong)

- Performed data cleaning and created dashboards for National Network of Libraries of Medicine (NNLM)
- Created R functions to automate data-cleaning processes

Research Assistant

### Feb 2015 – Aug 2017 Higher Education Learning and Persistence Lab, College of Education, University of Texas at Austin, Austin, TX (Dr. Fong)

- Collected documents and coded data for meta-analyses on psychosocial factors and critical thinking of community college students
- Conducted meta-analyses to examine growth- and fixed-mindset profiles and associations with stress, need satisfaction, coping strategies, fear of failure

### **TEACHING EXPERIENCE**

Computing Assistant

## Sep 2021 – Dec 2021 EDPSY 576: Multilevel Modeling, College of Education, University of Washington, Seattle, WA (Dr. Sanders)

Assisted class management (20+ graduate students) and explained analysis and interpretation of multilevel models using R

July 2020 & 2021 Instructor

#### Online Summer Workshop on Applied Statistics, Handong Global University, South Korea

Provided 30+ undergraduate and graduate students with the online workshop on statistical knowledge and research design using R and SPSS

Apr 2019 – Jun 2019 Teaching Assistant

### PSYCH 315: Understanding Statistics in Psychology, Department of Psychology, University of Washington, Seattle, WA (Dr. Nelson)

- Led two labs of 25+ undergraduate students and lectured on statistics using statistical concepts, analysis, and interpretation using SPSS and R
- Held office hours, facilitated class discussion, and graded students' exams

**Teaching Assistant** 

## Sep 2018 – Mar 2019 PSYCH 209: Fundamentals of Psychological Research, Department of Psychology, University of Washington, Seattle, WA (Drs. Culligan, Passer)

- Created exam questions, proctored exams, and graded them
- Led two labs of 25+ undergraduate students and lectured on research design
- Evaluated student's work, providing substantial written and oral feedback

Reader/Grader

# Sep 2017 – Dec 2017 EDPSY 302: Child Development and Learning, College of Education, University of Washington, Seattle, WA (Dr. Newman)

- Graded assignments including detailed feedback and scored exams
- Assisted class management (120+ undergraduate students) and explained development psychology concepts in classroom contexts

**Teaching Assistant** 

## Jan 2017 – May 2017 SDS 332: Statistical Models for the Health and Behavioral Sciences, Department of Statistics and Data Sciences, University of Texas at Austin, **Austin, TX** (Dr. Manheimer)

- Facilitated class discussions (120+ undergraduate students) as needed
- Monitored and taught via website, email, office hours, and in classroom
- Taught how to analyze data with SAS and graded assignments and exams

Sep 2015 - Dec 2015 Sep 2016 - Dec 2016 Teaching Assistant

## MKT282: Marketing Analytics & Applications, McComb School of Business, University of Texas at Austin, Austin, TX (Dr. Terhofstede)

- Provided statistical advice to 70+ MBA students via website and email to understand how marketing models can enhance decision making
- Evaluated student work, providing substantial written feedback

### **TEACHING EXPERIENCE (Cont'd)**

- $Mar\ 2013-Dec\ 2014$  English for Beginners, Yangdeok Elementary School, South Korea
- Developed lessons and instructed 1<sup>st</sup> and 2<sup>nd</sup> grade students, based on Korean government's English Learning Standards/grade-level expectations
  - government's English Learning Standards/grade-level expectations
  - Mar 2013 Dec 2014 Test of English for International Communication (TOEIC), Pohang Jeacheol Instructor Technical High School, South Korea
    - Developed and taught TOEIC Speaking classes for high school students
    - Built positive relationships with high school students, using developmentally appropriate activities and instructional strategies

### **PUBLICATIONS**

#### **Peer-reviewed articles**

- Elfers, A., Plecki, M., **Kim, Y.**, & Bei, N. (under review). How retention and mobility rates differ for teachers of color? *Teachers and Teaching*.
- Koo, K., **Kim, Y. W.**, Lee, Y., & Rodriquez, S. (under review). What does it mean to be an Asian in a pandemic? Exploring experiences of racism and discrimination among Asian international students in the United States during COVID-19. *Journal of Counseling Psychology*.
- Fong, C. J., Schallert, D. L., Williams, K. M., Williamson, Z. H., Lin, S., Chen, L., & **Kim, Y. W.** (2021). Making feedback constructive: The interplay of undergraduates' mastery goal orientation with feedback specificity and friendliness. *Educational Psychology*, 1-19. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/01443410.2021.1951671">https://doi.org/10.1080/01443410.2021.1951671</a>
- Koo, K., **Kim, Y. W.**, Lee, Y., & Nyunt, G. (2021). "It's my fault": Exploring experiences and mental wellness among Korean international graduate students. *Journal of International Students*, 11(4), 790-811. https://doi.org/10.32674/jis.v11i4.2801
- Fong, C. J. & **Kim, Y. W.** (2019). A clash of constructs? Re-examining grit in light of academic buoyancy and future time perspective. *Current Psychology*, 40(4), 1824-1837. https://doi.org/10.1007/s12144-018-0120-4
- Fong, C. J., Schallert, D. S., Williams, K. M., Williamson, Z. H., Warner, J. R., Lin, S., & Kim, Y. W. (2018). When feedback signals failure but offers hope for improvement: A process model of constructive criticism. *Thinking Skills and Creativity, 30,* 42-53. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tsc.2018.02.014">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tsc.2018.02.014</a>
- Fong, C. J., Williams, K. M., Williamson, Z. H., Lin, S., **Kim, Y. W.**, & Schallert, D. L. (2018). "Inside out": Student appraisals for achievement emotions regarding constructive criticism, positive feedback, and negative feedback on writing. *Motivation and Emotion*, 42, 236-257. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11031-017-9658-y
- Fong, C. J., Davis, C. W., Kim, Y., **Kim, Y. W.**, Marriott, L. A., & Kim, S. (2017). Psychosocial factors and community college student success: A meta-analytic investigation. *Review of Educational Research*, 87(2), 388-424. http://doi.org/10.3102/0034654316653479
- Fong, C. J., Kim, Y., Davis, C. W., Hoang, T., & **Kim, Y. W.** (2017). A meta-analysis on critical thinking and community college success. *Thinking Skills and Creativity, 26,* 71-83. <a href="http://doi.org/10.1016/j.tsc.2017.06.002">http://doi.org/10.1016/j.tsc.2017.06.002</a>

#### **Presentations**

- Koo, K., Kwon, J., & **Kim, Y**. (2022, April). *Strive to survive in a pandemic in a foreign country: Korean international students' well-being during covid-19*. Paper accepted for the Annual Meeting of the National Council on Measurement in Education.
- Bei, N., Sanders, E. A., Abe, N., & **Kim, Y**. (2021, June). *Measuring item process data with network analysis methods*. Paper presented at the Annual Meeting of the National Council on Measurement in Education.
- **Kim, Y.** (2021, April). *Understanding the role of academic achievement and psychosocial factors on adolescent depression: A latent growth model.* Paper presented at the Annual Meeting of the American Education Research Association.
- Koo, K, **Kim, Y.**, Lee, Y., & Rodriquez, S. (2021, April). What does it mean to be an Asian in a pandemic? Exploring experiences of racism and discrimination among Asian international students in the united states during covid-19. Paper presented at the Annual Meeting of the American Educational Research Association.
- Elfers, A., Plecki, M., **Kim, Y.**, & Bei, N. (2021, April). *Examining differences in the retention and mobility of teachers of color by racial/ethnic group*. Paper presented at the Annual Meeting of the American Educational Research Association.
- **Kim, Y.** (2020, April). Understanding the role of academic achievement and psychosocial factors on adolescent depression: A latent growth model. Paper accepted for the Annual Meeting of the Korean-American Educational Researchers Association, San Francisco, CA. (Conference canceled)
- Koo, K., & **Kim, Y.** (2020, April). The effectiveness of focusing art therapy on PTSD and cultural adjustment among North Korean refugee girls. Paper accepted for the Annual Meeting of the Korean-American Educational Researchers Association, San Francisco, CA. (Conference canceled)
- **Kim, Y.** (2020, April). Executive function difficulty, self-esteem, happiness, gender, and parent's income as the predictors of digital addiction. Paper accepted at the Annual Meeting of the American Educational Research Association, San Francisco, CA. (Conference canceled)
- Koo, K., **Kim, Y.**, Lee, Y., & Nyunt, G. (2020, April). What makes them happy? A qualitative study on Korean international graduate students' experiences and psychological wellbeing. Paper accepted at the Annual Meeting of the American Educational Research Association, San Francisco, CA. (Conference canceled)
- **Kim, Y.** (2019, April). *Trajectories of parents' socioeconomic status, child-parent interaction, children's self-control, school readiness, and academic performance.* Paper presented at the Annual Meeting of the American Educational Research Association, Toronto, ON.
- Koo, K., **Kim, Y.**, & Lee, Y. (2019, April). What makes them happy? Korean international graduate students' personal and professional experiences and emotional health. Paper presented at the Annual Meeting of the Korean-American Educational Researchers Association, Toronto, ON.
- Koo, K., **Kim, Y.**, & Lee, Y. (2019, March). What makes them happy? Asian international graduate students' personal and professional experiences and emotional health. Paper presented at the Annual Meeting of the American College Personnel Association, Boston, MA.

#### **Presentations (Cont'd)**

- Fong, C. J., Davis, C., Li, D., & **Kim, Y.** (2017, April). A meta-analysis of noncognitive factors and community college student success at 4-year institutions. Paper presented at the Annual Meeting of the American Educational Research Association, San Antonio, TX.
- Fong, C. J., **Kim, Y. W.**, Lin, S., & Hoang, T. (2017, April). *Do Noncognitive Interventions Enhance Community College Student Success? A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis*. Paper presented at the Annual Meeting of the American Educational Research Association, San Antonio, TX.
- Williamson, Z. H., Fong, C. J., Lin, S., Williams, K. M., **Kim, Y. W.**, & Schallert, D. L., (2017, April). *Self-Kindness in the Face of Criticism: Self-Compassion Influences Undergraduates' Perceptions of Constructive Feedback.* Paper presented at the Annual Meeting of the American Educational Research Association, San Antonio, TX.
- Fong, C. J., Davis, C., Li, D., **Kim, Y. W.**, & Hartman, C. E. (2016, August). *A meta-analysis of noncognitive factors and community college transfer student success at four-year institutions*. Paper presented at the Texas Higher Education Symposium, Austin, TX.
- Fong, C. J., Kim, Y., Davis, C. W., **Kim, Y. W.**, Marriott, L. A., & Kim, S. (2016, April). Psychosocial and self-regulatory correlates of community college student success: A systematic review and meta-analysis. Paper presented at the Annual Meeting of the American Educational Research Association, Washington, D.C.
- Fong, C. J., Schallert, D. L., Williams, K. M., Williamson, Z. H., Lin, S., Chen, L., **Kim, Y. W.** (2016, April). *Making feedback constructive: The interplay of undergraduates' mastery goal orientation with feedback specificity and friendliness*. Paper presented at the Annual Meeting of the American Educational Research Association, Washington, D.C.
- Lin, S., Fong, C. J., & **Kim, Y.** (2016, April). *Make up your mind: A person-centered approach to growth and fixed mindsets among Chinese undergraduates*. Paper presented at the Chinese American Education Research & Development Association, Washington, D.C.
- Kim, Y., Fong, C. J., Davis, C. W., Hoang, T., & **Kim, Y. W**. (2016, March). *A meta-analysis on critical thinking and community college student achievement*. Paper presented at the Council for the Study of Community Colleges Annual Meeting, Plano, TX.

#### **SERVICE**

Student Representative

Aug 2021 – Current Student Support Chair	•	Associated Students of the College of Education (ASCE), University of Washington, Seattle
Aug 2021 – Current GSC Liaison	•	AERA Division D Graduate Student Committee (GSC) Liaison, American Educational Research Association, Washington, D.C.
Apr 2021 – Jun 2021 Mentor	•	Next Generation Mentorship Program (NGMP), Office of Student Diversity and Inclusion, College of Education, University of Washington, Seattle
Oct 2020 – Current Ad-hoc Reviewer	•	Journal of International Students
Jul 2020 & Apr 2021 Panelist	•	Webinar: Racism and racialized identities: The experience among Asian international students in the United States, ACPA Commission for Global Dimensions of Student Development, Washington, D.C.
Jul 2019 – Jan 2020	•	New Hire Search Committee, Measurement & Statistics, College of

Education, University of Washington, Seattle